<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

<!-- generator="WordPress/3.9.1" created="2014-07-28 15:56" -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

	<item>
				<title>Magnum Maximization</title>
		<link>http://54.88.235.178/?p=14601</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[RichardMann]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dev.americanrifleman.org/?p=14601</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Ruger has redesigned its GP100 and Blackhawk revolvers to accommodate one of the newest, and best-received, revolver cartridges to date: the .327 Federal Mag. At a time when AR-type rifles and compact, semi-automatic handguns are the most popular sellers, you may think Ruger has taken an overzealous step. I don&rsquo;t. Both the Blackhawk and GP100 have illustrious reputations, and for those who really understand ballistics, the .327 Federal Mag. makes perfect sense. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">In 1953 Ruger introduced a little single-action, .22 Long Rifle revolver known as the Single-Six. The gun put <a href="http://www.ruger.com/" target="_blank">Ruger</a> on the map because it shot well and sold even better. It was also the forerunner of the larger <a href="http://www.americanrifleman.org/ArticlePage.aspx?id=2280&amp;cid=26" target="_blank">Blackhawk</a>; a center-fire single-action that has been chambered in a variety of cartridges. Single-Six and Blackhawk revolvers received an upgrade in 1973, which included a transfer bar safety, and they became known as &ldquo;New Models.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">In 1984 the Single-Six was chambered for the .32 H&amp;R Mag. I bought one with a 51/2-inch barrel and used it extensively as a trail gun. My affair with the .32 H&amp;R Mag. never ended; I&rsquo;ve owned several Single-Sixes and even a Marlin 1894 lever gun chambered for it. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Because of Harrington &amp; Richardson&rsquo;s less-than-robust revolvers, the performance of its .32 H&amp;R Mag. cartridge was actually restrained. That kept maximum operating pressures at less than 21,000 p.s.i., which was somewhat anemic when compared to magnum revolver cartridges, which are loaded to more than 30,000 p.s.i. Even though handloads could boost performance in strong guns, the .32 H&amp;R Mag. never sold with gusto. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Two years ago, when Ruger and Federal teamed up to launch the .327 Federal Mag. in the six-shot SP101, I immediately ordered one. The allure was a compact six-shot, double-action revolver offering terminal ballistics similar to a .357 Mag. Additionally, the revolver would also fire .32 S&amp;W, .32 S&amp;W Long and .32 H&amp;R Mag. ammunition. That SP101 has spent many hours on my hip in an El Paso Saddlery Tom Threepersons holster. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">The .327 Federal Mag. is a different animal than the .32 H&amp;R Mag. because it has a longer case and is loaded to a maximum operating pressure of 45,000 p.s.i. The strength of Ruger revolvers is well established, and both the Blackhawk and GP100 are capable of withstanding all the forces of the .327 Federal Mag. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>The Blackhawk</strong> <br />To take advantage of the .327 Federal Mag.&rsquo;s power Ruger is offering an all-stainless, 51/2-inch-barreled version of its single-action Blackhawk revolver. Outwardly, this newest Blackhawk is virtually identical to one in .357 Mag. built on the XR3 RED grip frame with a notable exception. When you swing open the loading gate and start shoving those slender, yet powerful, .327 Federal Mag. cartridges into the cylinder you realize that it will take eight to fill the gun. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">If you are familiar with the Blackhawk design, you&rsquo;ll also notice a difference in the sound and feel of the action when cocking it. This is a product of the eight-shot cylinder. Everything else, to include the fully adjustable rear sight, transfer-bar safety and rosewood stocks is just as it is on other Blackhawks. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">For those who like to hunt deer and smaller game with a handgun, a Blackhawk in .357 Mag. has been a popular choice. With good bullets it will work just fine at ranges most shooters are capable of hitting with open sights. This newest Blackhawk in .327 Federal Mag. is just as capable but has the added versatility of firing .32 S&amp;W, .32 S&amp;W Long and .32 H&amp;R Mag. as well. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">I&rsquo;m sure the first question on the minds of single-action aficionados is, &ldquo;Why didn&rsquo;t Ruger just chamber the Single-Six for the .327 Federal Mag. since it was already established as a platform for the .32 H&amp;R Mag.?&rdquo; For one, the overall length of a .327 Federal Mag. cartridge is too great to work in the cylinder of a Single-Six. And it is not, as some have erroneously assumed, a ladies&rsquo; gun. The recoil in a 28-ounce SP101 is, to put it mildly, brisk. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Nope, Ruger got it right. The Blackhawk in .327 Federal Mag. is a 48-ounce handgun that balances well and is comfortable to shoot even with full-power loads. The added advantage of the two extra shots is probably not that important for hunting large game, but for small game, particularly while using one of the less potent .32-cal. cartridges, they could come in handy. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Ruger seems to have a knack for knowing what shooters want. The .327 Federal Mag. Blackhawk was a no-brainer, and its SP101 in the same chambering makes for a good, double-action carry gun. The 3-inch barrel, however, is a bit short for duty or hunting. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>The GP100</strong> <br />A heavier- and longer-barreled GP100 was logical. The GP100 is the latest evolution of the double-action line of Ruger revolvers. It was introduced in 1986. Soon after, Ruger phased out its Speed Six and Security Six models. The GP100 was intended to appeal to the law enforcement and security officer revolver market. Being chambered in .357 Mag. meant the gun would also fire .38 Spl. standard and +P loads. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Ruger&rsquo;s newest GP100 has a model designation of KGP-4327-7, which describes the revolver very well. The &ldquo;K&rdquo; means it&rsquo;s manufactured of all-stainless steel while the &ldquo;4&rdquo; refers to the 4.2-inch barrel and &ldquo;327&rdquo; the chambering. The most unique feature of the revolver is represented by the final character &ldquo;7&rdquo; which signifies this latest GP100 holds seven cartridges. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Because the .327 Federal Mag. is slightly smaller in diameter than the .357 Mag., it made prefect sense to drill seven holes instead of six in the GP100&rsquo;s 1.54-inch-diameter cylinder. A seven-shot GP100 in .327 Federal Mag. weighs exactly the same as a six-shot GP100 in .357 Mag. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Like all GP100s, with the exception of a 3-inch-barreled, fixed-sight version, the seven-shot .327 has a fully adjustable rear sight. The front sight can be easily replaced with various aftermarket tritium or fiber-optic versions. The GP100 I tested had a nice double-action trigger and as good a single-action trigger as I&rsquo;ve pulled. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Ruger currently catalogs six GP100 revolvers. All, including the newest in .327 Federal Mag., have been upgraded with a much softer, black rubber, Hogue Monogrip. This replaces the rubber, compact grips with walnut insert panels that have become a distinguishing characteristic of the GP100. The new grip is larger and makes the GP100 a bit more difficult to conceal, but the improvement in how the gun feels in-hand and the extra control offered during recoil is worth the trade. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Professionals and civilians looking for a double-action duty, personal protection, hunting or trail revolver will appreciate the ruggedness and value GP100s offer. Now they can have a higher-capacity GP100, similar in power to the .357 Mag. but with added versatility. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">So, should you should trade in your .357 Mag. for one of these .327 Federal Mag. revolvers? Nope. But if you&rsquo;re looking for a powerful and versatile revolver, one of these new Rugers is a good place to start.</p>
<p>Read <a href="http://www.americanrifleman.org/ArticlePage.aspx?id=2340&amp;cid=1" target="_blank">Understanding .327 Federal Mag. Ballistics</a> and <a href="http://www.americanrifleman.org/ArticlePage.aspx?id=2341&amp;cid=1" target="_blank">Leather for Ruger's Latest .327s.</a></span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img style="border: 0pt none;" src="http://americanrifleman.org/WebContent/images/articles/327mag-table1.gif" alt="Table 1" width="640" height="178" /></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><img style="border: 0pt none;" src="http://americanrifleman.org/WebContent/images/articles/327mag-table2.gif" alt="Table 2" width="640" height="449" /></p>
<p style="text-align: left; padding-left:6px;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>WARNING:</strong> Technical data and information contained herein are intended to provide information based upon the limited experience of individuals under specific conditions and circumstances. They do not detail the comprehensive training, procedures, techniques and safety precautions that are absolutely necessary to properly carry on similar activity. READ THE NOTICE AND DISCLAIMER ON THE CONTENTS PAGE OF THIS MAGAZINE. ALWAYS CONSULT COMPREHENSIVE REFERENCE MANUALS AND BULLETINS OF PROPER TRAINING REQUIREMENTS, PROCEDURES, TECHNIQUES AND SAFETY PRECAUTIONS BEFORE ATTEMPTING ANY SIMILAR ACTIVITIES.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left; padding-left:6px;">&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Ruger has upped the ante of chamber count in their Blackhawk and GP100 revolvers in .327 Fed.]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>14601</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2010-04-13 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2010-04-13 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>magnum-maximization</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="handguns"><![CDATA[Handguns]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="handguns-2"><![CDATA[handguns]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="magnum-maximization"><![CDATA[Magnum Maximization]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="richard-mann"><![CDATA[Richard Mann]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="ruger"><![CDATA[Ruger]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="ruger-blackhawk"><![CDATA[Ruger Blackhawk]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="ruger-gp100"><![CDATA[ruger gp100]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="sturm-ruger"><![CDATA[sturm ruger]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_action_date</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[5/3/2010 8:34:54 AM]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2312]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_parent</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[0]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_parent_order</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[0]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_type</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_author_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[9]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_by_line</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[By Richard Mann]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_cat_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[18]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_front</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-4/2010413172327-rr130_fs.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_main</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-4/2010413172327-rr130_ms.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_thumb</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-4/2010413172327-rr130_t.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_in_magazine</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[True]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_pdf</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[none]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>auto_format</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[no]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>auto_quote</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[no]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_thumbnail_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[16795]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>A Half-Century of Service</title>
		<link>http://54.88.235.178/?p=14604</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[AngusMcClellan]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dev.americanrifleman.org/?p=14604</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">The NRA is well-known for its efforts in protecting the individual Right to Keep and Bear Arms, but its achievements in helping to train and prepare those to whom we&rsquo;ve granted the power to enforce the law are relatively unknown to the public at large. This is puzzling because, even though the NRA Law Enforcement Division (LED) has now trained firearm instructors for 50 years, NRA as a whole has ties with the law enforcement community that go back to 1916, and perhaps even further. The NRA has long recognized the importance of bolstering the strength of our common self-defense through training programs and lobbying, and for decades has been one of the primary forces in helping those who help protect us. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Police and other common forces have but one purpose in a free and just society, as expressed by Fr&eacute;d&eacute;rich Bastiat, political economist and member of the French assembly, in his 1850 work <em>The Law:</em> &ldquo;to do only what the individual forces have a natural and lawful right to do: to protect persons, liberties, and properties; to maintain the right of each, and to cause justice to reign over all.&rdquo; The Founding Fathers knew this, and as the times changed with advanced technology and its use by today&rsquo;s vilest criminals and terrorists, Americans recognized a need to create additional lines of defense to further protect themselves from society&rsquo;s worst. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Troops in all branches take oaths reflecting this purpose, and police officers often adopt a code of ethics that further resonates with Bastiat&rsquo;s words on our &ldquo;common force&rdquo;: </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">&ldquo;As a Law Enforcement Officer, my fundamental duty is to serve mankind; to safeguard lives and property; to protect the innocent against deception, the weak against oppression or intimidation, and the peaceful against violence or disorder; and to respect the Constitutional rights of all persons to liberty, equality and justice.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">No simple task by any means. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">With this year marking the 50th anniversary of the NRA&rsquo;s LED, it&rsquo;s time to take a look at the division&rsquo;s history and honor its contributions to the military, the law-enforcement community, and everyday citizens who&rsquo;ve benefited from its tireless efforts to strengthen public safety. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>The Early Years</strong> <br />Staff writer Frank J. Kahrs outlined a basic firearm training program for law enforcement officers in an article published in the November 1916 issue of <em>Arms and the Man</em>, the predecessor to <em>The American Rifleman</em>. Less than a decade later the NRA established a police qualification program, and teams from around the country were going to Camp Perry, Ohio, to test their skills against some of the best marksmen of the day. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Police departments were invited to send officers to Camp Perry for training as early as 1920, and the NRA first invited police chiefs from around the country to send teams to compete in the National Matches in 1924. The NRA, in close conjunction with the National Board for the Promotion of Rifle Practice (NBPRP), overseer of the Civilian Marksmanship Program (CMP), established at Camp Perry the Special Police School in 1926 under the Small Arms Firing School, which included a tactical course called &ldquo;Hogan&rsquo;s Alley.&rdquo; It consisted of makeshift buildings with reappearing silhouettes to simulate urban shoot-outs. Although elementary compared to today&rsquo;s advanced tactical courses, Hogan&rsquo;s Alley and other programs were leaps forward in the quickly evolving world of police firearm training&mdash;and not without good reason. The Roaring &rsquo;20s brought with it the bootleggers and, soon after, the likes of John Dillinger and Bonnie and Clyde, who demonstrated a shift in tools and tactics hardened criminals were using in pursuit of the dishonest dollar: use more guns, use bigger guns, and shoot anyone who gets in the way. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">A Police Section was created at the NRA&rsquo;s Washington, D.C., headquarters in 1930 in response to law enforcement&rsquo;s growing presence at the National Matches. In 1927, 2,000 policemen from around the country enrolled in a new qualification program; the NRA mailed targets to competitors who, with three witnesses, returned their targets to the headquarters for rankings as marksmen, sharpshooters or experts. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Despite lack of funding in the early years of the Depression, NRA-sponsored police training and qualification helped the Los Angeles Police Dept. pistol team become the first law enforcement squad to win the National Pistol Trophy Team Match in 1936, seizing the title from the once-dominant National Guard pistol teams. Funding returned, and although it appeared that NRA police qualification, training and competition might be on the rise in the United States, confronting the war machines of Imperialist Japan and Nazi Germany required a diversion of firearm materials and training directly into the war effort. The Police School folded. Police and civilian competition came to a grinding halt after Japan&rsquo;s bombing of Pearl Harbor, and during World War II the NRA focused primarily on helping to train the military and on training civilians through the Office of Civilian Defense.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p>


<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>The Rise Of NRA LED</strong> <br />The National Rifle and Pistol Matches returned to Camp Perry in 1953, but it wasn&rsquo;t until 1956 that the Police School was resurrected to strengthen the training of a new generation of law enforcement. The NRA went a step further in 1960 by creating an entirely new program for NRA Police Firearms Instructor certifications. This was the birth of the NRA&rsquo;s modern Law Enforcement Division, and the objective was simple: Train law enforcement instructors to NRA standards, and then return them to their respective departments to train individual officers; sanction at-home training and qualification courses that meet NRA standards; and encourage LE teams to compete in the National Matches. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Since 1960, the predominate focus of the NRA&rsquo;s law enforcement activities has been training instructors. As an extension of its Firearm Instructor training program, the NRA organized the first National Police Pistol Championships in 1962, today known as the National Police Shooting Championships (NPSC). The championships have been held in Indiana, Mississippi, Iowa, and are today held in Albuquerque, N.M. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Organized primarily as an individual and team accuracy-based competition, the Police Pistol Championships soon came to include the Police Pistol Combat (PPC) competition, still in existence today. Competitors shot at targets from 7 to 50 yards away with .38 Spl. or .357 Mag. revolvers in a variety of shooting positions. The first year saw 140 officers and 20 teams competing, and by 1969 there was a shotgun match consisting of skeet, trap and B-27 silhouette paper targets. By 1978 some 900 officers were competing&mdash;and that was just in the National Championships. The year 1981 saw 310 registered, approved, and Regional Championship tournaments with 11,425 total competitors. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">By 1968 there were 3,138 active Police Firearms Instructors who trained 56,767 officers. These included officers from small-town departments, from the Border Patrol and even White House Security. An article published in <em>American Rifleman</em> in the mid-1960s outlined three basic police training objectives of the times: to identify targets and engage quickly in a variety of positions; to gain positive identification of one&rsquo;s target before engagement and ensure civilian safety; and to develop a desire in policemen to shoot properly and accurately to encourage recreational practice. Teaching those objectives 40 years ago was as valuable then as it is today. But as law enforcement evolved from Smith &amp; Wesson Model 10 revolvers and over-starched duty shirts to the Wonder Nine semi-automatics and Kevlar ballistic vests, so too did the nature of police instructor training at the NRA. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>Recognize, Adapt, Overcome</strong> <br />In 1965 the first modern so-called &ldquo;urban riot&rdquo; shook the law-enforcement community to its roots. California Highway Patrolman Lee Minikus pulled over and arrested a belligerent and intoxicated driver in the South Central Los Angeles Watts neighborhood, sparking a six-day riot of burning, looting, beatings and general mayhem. Mobs targeted liquor stores and pawn shops, throwing Molotov cocktails and shooting at firemen and police. Law-enforcement personnel were overwhelmed, and only by calling in some 14,000 National Guardsmen was the situation brought under control. Other social upheaval during the 1960s and 1970s, in addition to the influx of inner-city gangs, drugs and violence, pushed law enforcement&rsquo;s call for more advanced tactics and training up through the 1980s. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">In 1979 the NRA consolidated the various law enforcement-related programs into the NRA Police Activities Division, today known as the Law Enforcement Division. The ultimate goal was essentially the same as before: train instructors and promote competitions for qualified law enforcement personnel as an extension of training. Provide law enforcement the tools needed to win armed confrontations. By this time NRA-certified instructors had collectively trained more than a million law-enforcement officers, and LED continued to grow. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">As an expansion of its 1978 Gunsmithing Schools, the NRA offered a new Law Enforcement Armorers School to assigned department armorers in 1979. The classes covered the assembly, disassembly and repair of Colt, Ruger, and Smith &amp; Wesson revolvers, as well as Ithaca, Remington and Winchester pump shotguns. The semi-automatics hadn&rsquo;t quite taken the law-enforcement community by storm then, but by 1987 LED was hosting seminars on Beretta, Glock, Heckler &amp; Koch, SIG Arms and Smith &amp; Wesson pistols to aid the transition from wheelguns to autoloaders in 9 mm Luger. Today NRA hosts tuition-free armorer schools at its headquarters in Fairfax, Va. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Firearm Instructor Development Schools were also adapting. Training had been available to private security instructors as early as 1967, but the NRA created a new Security Firearms Program in 1976 to address particular training, materials and instruction most relevant to private security needs. The new Rifle Instructor School helped swell the ranks of active NRA instructors to 10,208 by 1986. The following year, the Long Range Rifle Instructor program was created to address law enforcement&rsquo;s trend toward incorporating snipers into its departments. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">A new Submachine Gun School was conducted in 1987 to accommodate the growing popularity of H&amp;K&rsquo;s MP5 for tactical applications. Recognizing the need for advanced training to subdue violent criminals and minimize police casualties, the law enforcement community was overcoming its prior shortcomings, and the NRA LED was right there to help provide officers with the tools needed to effectively get the job done.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p>


<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>From The 1990s To Today</strong> <br />As the training and competition programs continued to flourish, LED started expanding benefits and recognition of individual law enforcement officers. As Glen Hoyer, director of LED summarized, &ldquo;Although we are still very focused on what we were founded on&mdash;training and competition&mdash;we&rsquo;ve branched out into other areas, such as tuition-free armorer schools and information seminars to help law enforcement officers and agencies. We will continue to look at new opportunities to help our fellow law enforcement and military personnel.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Any NRA member and public law enforcement officer killed in the line of duty receives a $25,000 life insurance benefit, in addition to his dependents being eligible for college tuition scholarships. Millions of dollars have gone to the grieving families of some of the country&rsquo;s most courageous officers. Dependents of retired and active police who are NRA members are also eligible for tuition assistance. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">In 1993, NRA began recognizing an Officer of the Year who exhibits &ldquo;exceptional valor, public service, and dedication to the principles of our Constitutional heritage.&rdquo; And the award is not given lightly. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">The 2005 Officer of the Year was awarded to NRA member and Officer James D. Niggemeyer of the Columbus, Ohio, Division of Police. On Dec. 8, 2004, a band was playing at a nightclub in Columbus when an armed and obsessed paranoid schizophrenic stormed the stage and began opening fire. Panicked nightclub patrons flooded the police switchboard with reports of an armed madman unloading round after round into musicians, employees and fans. Niggemeyer was patrolling nearby and entered a back door within three minutes of the first call. He maneuvered to the stage to get a clear view of the attacker, only to find the lunatic 20 feet away with a hostage in a headlock, pressing a handgun to the man&rsquo;s temple. With no other option, Niggemeyer waited for his moment of opportunity, and in a professional display of precision, shot the man in the face with a 12-gauge Remington 870. At his death, the assailant still had 35 rounds of ammunition. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Today LED has trained more than 50,000 instructors, with about 2,000 new instructors trained each year as the program continues to expand. With such a multitude of applicants, instructor classes are dispersed throughout the country and are held on a regular basis. Classes today include Handgun, Handgun/Shotgun, Tactical Shooting (pistol/long gun), Tactical Shotgun, Patrol Rifle, Select-Fire, and Precision (Scoped) Rifle Instructor. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">LED maintains one of only a few nationally recognized firearm training classes as confirmed by a number of court decisions. Some states, such as Pennsylvania, have officially recognized the NRA as an acceptable standard, as have the military and agencies such as the Nuclear Regulatory Commission. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">NRA&rsquo;s LED has been to Afghanistan, Japan and other countries to help train our military. In fact, just before the invasion of Afghanistan in 2001, a major in the Marine Corps came to LED to train his troops because he knew that today&rsquo;s wars are different from past wars. Nowadays, our troops are heavily involved in urban warfare and must focus more on protecting the innocent as well as eliminating the enemy, just as our police officers do on a daily basis here in the United States&mdash;and the major knew that LED has been hosting this type of training for a long time. &ldquo;Who better to train us than the NRA?&rdquo; he asked. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">A few years ago LED added a new breed of competitions to its standard PPC. The Tactical Police Competition (TPC) is essentially a 3-gun-type match consisting of pistol, rifle and shotgun shooting in timed events. Competitors often transition from one gun to another, depending on the nature of the course. The events are divided into skill-based and scenario-based courses, with the former focusing on officers&rsquo; &ldquo;abilities in handling, accuracy and overall proficiency with a given firearm system under set conditions.&rdquo; Scenario-based courses are hypothetical law-enforcement encounters in which officers must use their own tactics and skills to resolve situations. TPC is open to law enforcement officers, members of the U.S. military and private-sector law enforcement officers. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">The Eddie Eagle program was recently incorporated into LED as well, and today has reached more than 23 million children, teaching them how to safely react if they come across a firearm. &ldquo;Stop, Don&rsquo;t Touch, Leave the Area, Tell an Adult&rdquo; has been ingrained into the minds of children all across the country. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Preserving and bettering the American way of life for future generations is one of society&rsquo;s highest duties. Protecting their right to life, liberty and property as our Founding Fathers envisioned depends on remaining vigilant and prepared today. With a half-century under its belt and millions of the finest military and law enforcement personnel continually benefiting from its training and services, it appears the NRA Law Enforcement Division will continue to lead the country as one of the premier law enforcement firearm training organizations for generations to come. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><em>For more information on instructor development courses, competitions, Eddie Eagle, law enforcement benefits and other related information, visit</em> <a href="http://www.nrahq.org/law/" target="_blank">http://www.nrahq.org/law/</a><em> or call</em> (703) 267-1640.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The NRA Law Enforcement Division celebrates its 50th Anniversary. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>14604</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2010-04-13 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2010-04-13 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>a-half-century-of-service</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="a-half-century-of-service"><![CDATA[A Half-Century of Service]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="angus-mcclellan"><![CDATA[Angus McClellan]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="news"><![CDATA[news]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="news-rifles"><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="nra-law-enforcement-division"><![CDATA[NRA Law Enforcement Division]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="rifles"><![CDATA[Rifles]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="rifles-2"><![CDATA[rifles]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_action_date</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[4/13/2010 5:18:36 PM]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2309]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_parent</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[0]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_parent_order</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[0]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_type</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_author_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[9]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_by_line</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[By Angus McClellan, AR Associate Editor]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_cat_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_front</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-4/2010413171328-dickkram_fs.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_main</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-4/2010413171328-dickkram_ms.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_thumb</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-4/2010413171328-dickkram_t.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_in_magazine</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[True]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_pdf</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[none]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>auto_format</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[no]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>auto_quote</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[no]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_thumbnail_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[16798]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	<item>
				<title>Para USA: Coming to America</title>
		<link>http://54.88.235.178/?p=14607</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[BrianSheetz]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://dev.americanrifleman.org/?p=14607</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Although the prefix &ldquo;para&rdquo; is often taken to mean &ldquo;related to,&rdquo; it also can be construed as &ldquo;beyond.&rdquo; That second sense more appropriately characterizes the firearm company that today is based in Charlotte, N.C., and is known as Para USA, but that only 25 years ago was an upstart in an Ontario, Canada, suburb making a single, unique, non-firearm product. Para-Ordnance, as it was then known, was built on a partnership between two friends and on the idea that unique, innovative products would capture the imagination of shooters looking for something different. While its first foray into things that shoot was less than commercially successful, it nonetheless established the founders&rsquo; talents for combining innovative design with compelling marketing. By the second time around, that formula proved to be dead-on and aimed at no less a target than the reinvention of the greatest firearm in its category. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>Reinventing A Masterpiece</strong> <br />The Para-Ordnance product line began inauspiciously enough in 1985 with the development of a non-firearm product called the Model 85 Dye Marking Tactical Machine Pistol. The black polymer &ldquo;gun&rdquo; bore a striking resemblance to a real MAC 10, but used light primer charges to shoot gelatinous die capsules without potentially injurious wads. When introduced to the market in 1987 an informative and, for the time, flashy brochure marketed the blowback-operated Model 85 on the strength of its realistic appearance and sound, 440 fps velocity, and even a 1,200-r.p.m. full-automatic firing mode. It suggested that the Model 85 would allow SWAT teams to train in tactics, foresters to mark trees for cutting, and stunt men and actors to create the impression of a real gunfight. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">The Model 85 was the brainchild of engineer Ted Szabo, a 20-year veteran moldmaker who appreciated firearms not only for their functionality, but for the freedom they represented&mdash;his family had fled their native Hungary to avoid Communist oppression. What&rsquo;s more, Szabo had a knack for understanding how firearms worked along with the rare talent and determination to see their shortcomings as an opportunity to improve them for greater functionality. Szabo&rsquo;s partner and friend, Thanos Polyzos, the son of Greek immigrants and an attorney practicing criminal law, had not only an appreciation for firearms but a keen sense of the market forces that drove their sales. He was also comfortable with regulatory paperwork such as that required by the U.S. Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco &amp; Firearms. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Both men knew that the Model 85&mdash;as unique, well-engineered and, doubtless, ahead of its time as it was&mdash;simply didn&rsquo;t have mass market appeal. Fortunately, a confluence of circumstances created an opportunity for far greater success just as Model 85 sales dissipated. The new idea had been in the back of Szabo&rsquo;s mind since the early 1970s. An admirer of John Browning&rsquo;s classic M1911 pistol, he felt that its magazine capacity of seven rounds was unnecessarily limited, requiring too many changes&mdash;especially during competitions, which were gaining in popularity at the time. In addition, the U.S. military had for several years been considering a replacement for the long-serving M1911 partly for the same reason&mdash;that of capacity, or &ldquo;firepower.&rdquo; The Army&rsquo;s selection of the Beretta M9 in 1985 marked the midpoint in the popular gun press&rsquo; exploitation of the so-called &ldquo;Wonder Nine&rdquo; wars that endlessly debated the merits of a defensive or military pistol containing a dozen or more 9 mm Luger cartridges versus one containing fewer, larger-caliber cartridges. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Most people approached the argument from the vantage point of which existing design merited the greater favor; Szabo came at it from the idea of blending the best attributes of each platform and set about to create a better mousetrap. By the 1988 Shooting, Hunting, Outdoor Trade Show, he had completed the solution: a higher-capacity, extra-wide M1911-style frame and double-stack magazine kit that could be retrofitted to the slide assembly of an existing single-stack gun. Polyzos confidently announced the gun in a letter to then <em>American Rifleman</em> Technical Editor Pete Dickey, whose breadth of experience made him difficult to impress. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">The kit&rsquo;s features, however, were remarkable. The frame was a precision, light alloy investment casting that featured full-length rails, a thicker section around the slide stop pin hole, a cast-in plunger tube and a beveled magazine well&mdash;all of which added nothing to the weight of a complete gun and resulted in only a 1/8-inch thicker grip area including stocks. The magazine was a 13-round double-stack unit made of 0.028-inch-thick heat-treated steel and had an easily removable floorplate for cleaning and maintenance. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">The opening words in the <em>American Rifleman</em> &ldquo;Dope Bag&rdquo; review of the &ldquo;Para-Ordnance 13-Shot .45 Kit,&rdquo; stated, &ldquo;For two years a prototype of Para-Ordnance&rsquo;s aluminum frame for Colt&rsquo;s Government Model pistol has been a focal point at gun shows. It is now on the market. Its great attraction is its 13-shot magazine capacity (plus one in the chamber) that almost doubles the 7+1 capacity of the standard .45 ACP model. The many shooters who prefer .45s yet appreciate the greater capacities of 9 mms are the obvious sales targets, and that potential market is sizeable.&rdquo; It took a few years before the first complete pistol from Para-Ordnance appeared in the &ldquo;Dope Bag,&rdquo; which summed up the new gun by stating, &ldquo;The P14-45, then, lets the less adventurous soul who doesn&rsquo;t want to go on a scavenger hunt for parts enjoy the big 13-round capacity of the Para-Ordnance frame, a unit that has become popular both for defense and competition purposes.&rdquo; With the P14 45&rsquo;s release, Para-Ordnance had become a full-fledged firearm manufacturer.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p>


<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>Expanding The Brand</strong> <br />In the intervening years, the Para kit, and later, complete pistols sold briskly, and the company expanded its line to include dozens of M1911-based models including double-stack guns and, ironically, single-stack guns in all manner of sizes and with all manner of finishes and enhancements. In 1991, Polyzos shrewdly enlisted the marksmanship and showmanship skills of competitive pistol shooter Todd Jarrett, who became the face of Para pistols, winning countless titles and performing numerous feats designed to demonstrate the brand&rsquo;s inherent quality. To date <a href="http://www.para-usa.com/" target="_blank">Para USA</a> claims more than 100 championships including nine USPSA National titles and the IPSC World title. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">As Polyzos was busy expanding the business and cementing Para&rsquo;s reputation among shooters, gunwriters, and even some law enforcement officers, Szabo was turning out even more innovations for the famous Browning platform. In 1998, the company unveiled the Light Double Action (LDA) trigger system for its M1911-based pistols. With it, shooters finally could benefit from the familiarity of the M1911 platform without having to carry it in the &ldquo;cocked and locked&rdquo; condition that made some uncomfortable. The top-pivoted, smooth-faced trigger, which initially had a blade that appeared too slender in its fore-to-aft dimension, has been redesigned to be thicker in that regard and to have a serrated face. But the LDA&rsquo;s real beauty was beneath the surface. It offered a long, deliberate pull stroke with a relatively light letoff of approximately 6 pounds and was engineered with several internal safety features. The LDA represented Szabo&rsquo;s and Polyzos&rsquo; finest hour as even Colt had been unable to produce and market a commercially successful double-action version of Browning&rsquo;s masterpiece during the nearly 90 years since its development. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">In 2003, Szabo launched his final improvement to the M1911 platform: the Para Power Extractor, a multipiece internal unit that fit into the M1911 slide assembly in the way that Browning&rsquo;s original extractor had, but that was articulated by means of four separate parts including a small coil spring. The Power Extractor not only offered greater purchase on the case rim, but alleviated the necessity of a traditional extractor&rsquo;s having to be precisely fitted to the gun. The company even offered a service of modifying conventional M1911 frames to accept the device. Today it is found across the Para line of pistols, be they single- or double-stack, full-size or compact. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Last year Para caught even the most astute industry observers off-guard by introducing the Para <a href="http://www.americanrifleman.org/ArticlePage.aspx?id=2070&amp;cid=4" target="_blank">Tactical Target Rifle</a>, or TTR. The company&rsquo;s first foray into long guns, the TTR is actually the brainchild of another firearm innovator, Allan Zitta, whose Z-M Weapons company developed the Delayed Impingement Gas System (DIGS) used in its LR-series AR-style rifles. Para USA now licenses the design, which can best be described as a combination of piston and direct-impingement systems. The rifle is a perfect fit for the Para paradigm in that it, too, was earlier available as a kit for retrofitting to a standard AR lower and because it exploits another of the most established platforms of its kind: Eugene Stoner&rsquo;s ArmaLite rifle. But the TTR&rsquo;s features push the AR into a different category altogether. The U-shaped channel inside its gas block results in lower port pressures, and the system&rsquo;s gas handling makes for a cleaner-running rifle with less carbon fouling and heat buildup in critical action parts such as the bolt. Other major benefits to the TTR&rsquo;s DIGS system include the lack of a buttstock-mounted buffer system, which means the rifle can incorporate a true side-folding stock that is hinged just behind the pistol grip. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>Coming To America</strong> <br />Reinvention is a consistent theme in the Para story. And despite the company&rsquo;s continuing product innovations, its most significant defining moment was its recent move to Pineville, N.C., a small suburb of Charlotte in America&rsquo;s traditional South. According to Polyzos, despite the years of Para&rsquo;s successes and the many satisfied American firearm consumers, some potential buyers simply couldn&rsquo;t get past the pistols&rsquo; Canadian origin. In addition, he believed that the M1911 was, at its core, an American product. He also hoped that the TTR had some potential as a competitor in future U.S. military rifle trials. So, in 2007, Polyzos began to evaluate several potential sites in the United States to which he could move the company. Among them North Carolina promised to be an ideal location with good access to transportation, a favorable business climate and, not least, a culture known for its hard work ethic. A bonus came in the form of prospective employees who came to the company with previous firearm-building experience. The company offered to transfer any of its Canadian workers who wished to make the move, and several key production personnel with invaluable experience accepted, which has contributed to the continuity of production generally and to quality control particularly. But the infusion of new blood into an established institution has proven to be the exact catalyst Para executives were looking for to advance the company to the next level. Many of Para USA&rsquo;s newest recruits are skilled workers with an unusual degree of previous experience in the realm of gunmaking, fitting and finishing.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p>


<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Among the staff of tool-and-die makers who transferred from Canada on work permits is Derek Beattie, who has been with Para for seven years and has 17 years&rsquo; experience as a moldmaker. Beattie runs a cubicle-size wire Electrical Discharge Machining (EDM) center that cuts the molds for the Metal Injection Molding (MIM) machine, which then forms metal or plastic into the specific shapes of small parts such as skeletonized triggers. He is quick to point out that the moldmaker&rsquo;s trade is essential not only to producing the necessary parts to build Para firearms, but to the fundamental understanding of the intricacies of how such parts must be designed and manufactured. &ldquo;Both [Ted Szabo] and his dad were moldmakers and very technical people, but they knew that they had to leave up to the moldmaker how to come up with the solution. That kind of understanding of the process leads to innovative thinking.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Seven-year Para veteran Neil Sevel makes a case for the contingent of workers who made the move to America, saying, &ldquo;It helps us in the transition and the training. The old quality is still here&mdash;we have a proven way.&rdquo; Acknowledging his new coworkers, he said, &ldquo;The guys we have here are all gun people&mdash;enthusiasts. A lot of them are working for a living doing the hobby they enjoy.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Many within the management team have a high degree of hands-on experience. One example is Ben Cook, the company&rsquo;s executive director for strategic development and customer relations. Cook was trained by a former U.S. Army Marksmanship Unit armorer, has been a part-time gunsmith, has built his own M1911-style pistols and spent the better part of four years training USMC instructors in close-quarters shooting techniques. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Cook and other managers can often be found on the factory floor where they have an easy rapport with workers such as Louie Ely, a stout American with a kind demeanor but an all-business attitude when he has a tool in his hand. In the assembly area, he skillfully places fire-control parts into frames, testing the triggers and hand-setting their leaf springs completely by feel. &ldquo;I built rifles before I came here,&rdquo; he says matter-of-factly. Nearby is Jeff Abernathy, a second-generation gunsmith who heeded Para&rsquo;s call to work at the new factory. Abernathy worked in his father&rsquo;s Mount Holly, N.C., gunshop where he &ldquo;cut his teeth&rdquo; on all kinds of firearms before deciding, about eight years ago, that he would concentrate on M1911-style pistols for IDPA and IPSC competition. That&rsquo;s when he caught Para pro shooter Todd Jarrett&rsquo;s attention, and before Abernathy knew it he was elbow-deep in components in the new Para factory. &ldquo;I want each gun to look the best it possibly can with 100 percent functionality,&rdquo; said Abernathy, adding, &ldquo;Quality is always the main priority.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;"><strong>Moving Beyond Expectations</strong> <br />Even as Para USA pistols near completion, quality control measures are stringently enforced. Ben Fritz, who has more than 30 years of manufacturing experience, including technical design, heads a cadre of workers he described as &ldquo;empowered to fail a gun at any point in the build process.&rdquo; At the indoor test range the quality control protocol includes a firing test with one proof round and 11 standard rounds of ammunition. The first magazine is fired for accuracy and the second for function. Throughout the process, but especially at the end, the team checks each gun for fit and finish, function and accuracy. Fritz documents any failures, looks for trends, analyzes them and develops solutions. &ldquo;We want to address every flaw. It&rsquo;s a quest for perfection and the only people we&rsquo;re looking for approval from is our customers.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">&ldquo;Ted Szabo was a genius, and the reason Thanos moved to the USA is because he knew the 1911 was an American gun. He wanted to take Para to the next level,&rdquo; said Fritz. Cook couldn&rsquo;t agree more although he is hesitant to reveal specifics about new developments in firearms, both pistols and rifles, the company has on the drawing board. In fact, some are already in shootable, prototype form and promise to be significant departures from the company&rsquo;s signature product lines. He also said the company will institute a number of specific changes to its products in coming months, hinting at such applications as nitride and tungsten DLC coatings to replace the sprayed-on coatings now in use as well as premium features such as tool steel fire-control components for certain models. In an entirely different type of project, Para USA has also inked a deal with the Single Action Shooting Society to produce an official Wild Bunch M1911 pistol. </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">&ldquo;Para is breaking-in as an organization just as a new gun breaks-in,&rdquo; Cook said. &ldquo;Relocation forced us to build a new organization, and now we&rsquo;re hitting our stride.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">Ted Szabo did not live to see Para USA become an American company. Before his death in 2007 at the age of 60, Szabo is reported to have said of his accomplishments regarding Para&rsquo;s enhancements to John Browning&rsquo;s masterpiece, &ldquo;I have always wanted to pick up where his design left off and carry the technology forward to the next level.&rdquo; </span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;"><span style="font-size: small;">He clearly accomplished that goal, and in the same fashion his friend and original partner, Thanos Polyzos, continues to guide the able force of Para USA workers on a course aimed at convincing American gun buyers that Para USA is not only all about innovating classic designs, but intends to go well beyond them into a future all its own.</span></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[Para USA goes beyond innovation with both classic firearms and designs all its own. ]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>14607</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date>2010-04-13 00:00:00</wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt>2010-04-13 00:00:00</wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status>open</wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status>open</wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name>para-usa-coming-to-america</wp:post_name>
		<wp:status>publish</wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type>post</wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
		<category domain="category" nicename="handguns"><![CDATA[Handguns]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="handguns-2"><![CDATA[handguns]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="m1911"><![CDATA[m1911]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="para"><![CDATA[para]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="para-usa"><![CDATA[para usa]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="para-usa-coming-to-america"><![CDATA[Para USA: Coming to America]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="para-ordnance"><![CDATA[PARA-Ordnance]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="semi-auto-handguns"><![CDATA[Semi-Auto]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="semi-auto"><![CDATA[semi-auto]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="tactical-target-rifle"><![CDATA[Tactical Target Rifle]]></category>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_action_date</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[6/17/2010 4:10:04 PM]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[2306]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_parent</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[0]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_parent_order</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[0]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_article_type</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[1]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_author_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[9]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_by_line</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[By Brian C. Sheetz, AR Executive Editor]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_cat_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[19]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_front</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-5/20105315439-para_fs.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_main</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-5/20105315439-para_ms.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_image_thumb</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[/Webcontent/images/2010-5/20105315439-w6845tar-5761_t.jpg]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_in_magazine</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[True]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>AR_pdf</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[none]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>auto_format</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[no]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>auto_quote</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[no]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_thumbnail_id</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[16801]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>friendly</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[ParaUSA]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
		<wp:postmeta>
			<wp:meta_key>_edit_last</wp:meta_key>
			<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[47]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
	</item>
	
	
	
</rss>
